<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs),
please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
(Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocappendix="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space
(using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<?rfc comments="no" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-muks-dnsop-dns-catalog-zones-01" ipr="trust200902">

  <front>

    <title>DNS catalog zones</title>

    <author fullname="Mukund Sivaraman" initials="M." surname="Sivaraman">
      <organization>Internet Systems Consortium</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>950 Charter Street</street>
	  <city>Redwood City</city>
	  <code>94063</code>
	  <region>CA</region>
	  <country>US</country>
	</postal>
	<email>muks@mukund.org</email>
	<uri>http://www.isc.org/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Stephen Morris" initials="S." surname="Morris">
      <organization>Internet Systems Consortium</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>950 Charter Street</street>
	  <city>Redwood City</city>
	  <code>94063</code>
	  <region>CA</region>
	  <country>US</country>
	</postal>
	<email>stephen@isc.org</email>
	<uri>http://www.isc.org/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ray Bellis" initials="R." surname="Bellis">
      <organization>Internet Systems Consortium</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>950 Charter Street</street>
	  <city>Redwood City</city>
	  <code>94063</code>
	  <region>CA</region>
	  <country>US</country>
	</postal>
	<email>ray@isc.org</email>
	<uri>http://www.isc.org/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Witold Krecicki" initials="W." surname="Krecicki">
      <organization>Internet Systems Consortium</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>950 Charter Street</street>
	  <city>Redwood City</city>
	  <code>94063</code>
	  <region>CA</region>
	  <country>US</country>
	</postal>
	<email>wpk@isc.org</email>
	<uri>http://www.isc.org/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date/>

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>Operations and Management Area</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <!-- <keyword>dns</keyword> -->

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes a method for automatic zone catalog
      provisioning and synchronization among DNS primary and secondary
      nameservers by storing and transferring the catalogs as regular
      DNS zones.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>DNS nameservers implement AXFR and IXFR for zone data
      synchronization among a zone's primary and secondary nameservers,
      but the list of zones served by the primary (called a catalog in
      <xref target="RFC1035" />) is not automatically synchronized. The
      administrator of a DNS nameserver farm has to synchronize such
      zone catalogs among primaries and their secondary nameservers
      manually or via an external application layer. This can be
      inconvenient, error-prone and dependent on the nameserver
      implementation.</t>

      <t>A method for automatic zone catalog provisioning and
      synchronization is useful, so that the zone catalog can be
      maintained in a reference location by an administrator, similar to
      zone data.</t>

      <t>This document describes one such method, in which the catalog
      is represented as a regular DNS zone called a "catalog zone", and
      transferred using DNS zone transfers. The representation of
      catalogs within DNS zones is specified and nameserver requirements
      are listed so that DNS implementations can support catalog
      zones.</t>

      <t>The contents and representation of catalog zones are described
      in <xref target="sec-catzones" />. Nameserver behavior is
      described in <xref target="sec-impl" />. A glossary of some terms
      used in this memo is provided in <xref target="sec-glossary"
      />.</t>

      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL"
      in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119" />.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Catalog zones" anchor="sec-catzones">
      <section title="Description">
	<t>A catalog zone is a specially crafted DNS zone that contains,
	as DNS zone data, a list of DNS zones called member zones,
	associated template zone configuration common to all its member
	zones, and zone-specific configuration that applies to a
	respective zone. An implementation of catalog zones MAY allow
	catalog zones to include other catalog zones, but template zone
	configuration present in a catalog zone only applies to its
	immediate member zones. A catalog zone is meant to be used to
	provision DNS catalogs to secondary nameservers via zone
	transfers, for the purpose of setting up member zones to be
	served from these secondary nameservers.</t>

	<t>A catalog zone uses some RR TYPEs such as PTR with alternate
	semantics for its purposes. Although this may be controversial,
	the situation is similar to other similar zone-based
	representations such as response-policy zones <xref target="RPZ"
	/>. A design criterion of catalog zones is that none of the RR
	TYPEs used therein may incur any additional section processing
	during DNS QUERY.</t>

	<t>Member zones' configuration is specified as a map of zone
	properties, represented as a subtree of a node <xref
	target="RFC1034" /> in the domain name space inside a catalog
	zone. This is described in <xref target="sec-map" />. Each zone
	property has a name and an associated value of a specific data
	type. Zone property value data types are described in <xref
	target="sec-types" />. A list of permitted zone property names
	and their data types is given in <xref target="sec-properties"
	/>.</t>

	<t>TBD: Transitive catalogs</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Resource record fields">
	<t>A catalog zone contains various resource records (RRs). They
	have NAME, TYPE, CLASS, TTL, RDLENGTH and RDATA as fields <xref
	target="RFC1035" />.</t>

	<t>The NAME field contains the owner name of the respective
	RR. As with all DNS zones, the owner name must be a child of the
	catalog zone name.</t>

	<t>The TYPE field depends on the type of catalog zone property
	value being represented. <xref target="sec-types" /> describes
	how various zone property value types are represented.</t>

	<t>The CLASS field of the RR MUST be set to IN(1) <xref
	target="RFC1035" />. This is because some RR TYPEs such as APL
	used by catalog zones are defined only for the IN CLASS.</t>

	<t>The TTL field's value is not specially defined by this
	memo. Catalog zones are for nameserver management only and are
	not intended for general querying.  Operators should use
	whatever value seems convenient for any management applications
	that may query the catalog zone.</t>

	<t>The RDLENGTH field contains the length of the RDATA
	field.</t>

	<t>The content of the RDATA field depends on the type of catalog
	zone property value being represented. <xref target="sec-types"
	/> describes how various zone property value types are
	represented.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="SOA and NS records at apex">
	<t>Similar to any other DNS zone, a catalog zone would be
	expected to have a syntactically correct SOA record and one or
	more NS records at its apex.</t>

	<t>The SOA record's SERIAL, REFRESH, RETRY and EXPIRE fields
	<xref target="RFC1035" /> are used during zone transfer. A
	catalog zone's SOA SERIAL field SHOULD increase when an update
	is made to the catalog zone's contents as per serial number
	arithmetic defined in <xref target="RFC1982" />. Otherwise,
	secondary nameservers may not notice updates to the catalog
	zone's contents.</t>

	<t>The SOA record's MINIMUM field's value is not specially
	defined by this memo. Although they are regular DNS zones,
	catalog zones contain only information for the management of a
	set of nameservers.  For this reason, operators may want to
	limit the systems able to query these zones.</t>

	<t>As catalog zones do not participate in the DNS, NS records at
	the apex are not used but they are still required so that
	catalog zones are syntactically correct DNS zones. No parent
	delegation for the catalog zone is required. Any valid DNS name
	can be used in the NSDNAME field of such NS records <xref
	target="RFC1035" /> and they MUST be ignored. A single NS RR
	with an NSDNAME field containing the absolute name "invalid."
	is recommended <xref target="RFC2606" />.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Zone properties map and owner names" anchor="sec-map">
	<t>Member zones' configuration is specified as a map of zone
	properties, represented as a subtree of a node <xref
	target="RFC1034" /> in the domain name space inside a catalog
	zone. A subtree of child nodes is used for a nested map,
	occuping another label level. A map element's key (property
	name) is represented in the label at that level. For example, if
	a catalog zone is named "catalog1.example.org." and contains a
	property with name "prop0", the corresponding owner name of the
	node representing that property is
	"prop0.catalog1.example.org."</t>

	<t>Zone property names are case-insensitive. Each zone property
	may use only one data type for its values. A list of permitted
	zone property names and their data types is given in <xref
	target="sec-properties" />.</t>

	<t>Many properties are single-valued, but some properties can be
	collections with thousands of values. An example is the list of
	member zones within a catalog zone, which can be larger than any
	single RDATA instance can allow. Multiple RRs are used to
	represent such properties.</t>

	<t>TBD: Currently a hashing method in owner names is used to
	split the elements of such properties with multiple RRs into
	individual RRsets, one per RR. This needs to be revisited as
	IXFR and DNS UPDATE both allow individual RRs within an RRset to
	be modified. The hashing method used is described in the
	appropriate property value data types in <xref
	target="sec-types" />.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Zone property value data types" anchor="sec-types">
	<section title="Strings" anchor="sec-string">
	  <t>A property with a string value is specified using a single
	  TXT RR <xref target="RFC1035" /> with owner name set to the
	  name of the property as a sub-domain of the catalog zone name,
	  and RDATA set to the property value.</t>

	  <t>For example, if a catalog zone is named
	  "catalog1.example.org." and contains a property "prop0" with
	  string value "Example", the corresponding RR would appear as
	  follows:</t>

	  <figure>
	    <artwork>
        prop0.catalog1.example.org. 3600 IN TXT "Example"
	    </artwork>
	  </figure>

	  <t>Here, "prop0" can contain multiple TXT RRs at that node of
	  the domain name space <xref target="RFC1034" />. The single
	  string property SHOULD be checked by the implementation.</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Booleans" anchor="sec-bool">
	  <t>A property with a boolean value is specified using a single
	  TXT RR with owner name set to the name of the property as a
	  sub-domain of the catalog zone name, and RDATA set to "true"
	  for true condition and "false" for false condition. The RDATA
	  is case-insensitive.</t>

	  <t>For example, if a catalog zone is named
	  "catalog1.example.org." and contains a property "active" with
	  boolean value false, the corresponding RR would appear as
	  follows:</t>

	  <figure>
	    <artwork>
        active.catalog1.example.org. 3600 IN TXT "false"
	    </artwork>
	  </figure>

	  <t>Here, "active" can contain multiple TXT RRs at that node of
	  the domain name space <xref target="RFC1034" />. The single
	  boolean property SHOULD be checked by the implementation.</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Integers" anchor="sec-int">
	  <t>A property with an integer value is specified using a
	  single TXT RR for signed integers or unsigned integers, with
	  owner name set to the name of the property as a sub-domain of
	  the catalog zone name, and RDATA set to the property
	  value.</t>

	  <t>A signed integer's TXT RDATA uses the representation of an
	  unsuffixed "integer constant" as defined in the C programming
	  language standard <xref target="ISO.9899.1990" /> (of the type
	  matching a 64-bit signed integer on that platform), with an
	  optional minus prefix. The representation MUST be specified
	  using a single &lt;character-string&gt; <xref target="RFC1034"
	  />.</t>

	  <t>An unsigned integer's TXT RDATA uses the representation of
	  an unsuffixed "integer constant" as defined in the C
	  programming language standard <xref target="ISO.9899.1990" />
	  (of the type matching a 64-bit unsigned integer on that
	  platform). The representation MUST be specified using a single
	  &lt;character-string&gt; <xref target="RFC1034" />.</t>

	  <t>For example, if a catalog zone is named
	  "catalog1.example.org." and contains a property "min-ttl" with
	  unsigned integer value 300, the corresponding RR would appear
	  as follows:</t>

	  <figure>
	    <artwork>
        min-ttl.catalog1.example.org. 3600 IN TXT "300"
	    </artwork>
	  </figure>

	  <t>Here, "min-ttl" can contain multiple TXT RRs at that node
	  of the domain name space <xref target="RFC1034" />. The single
	  integer property SHOULD be checked by the implementation.</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Floating-point values" anchor="sec-float">
	  <t>A property with a floating-point value is specified using a
	  single TXT RR with owner name set to the name of the property
	  as a sub-domain of the catalog zone name, and RDATA set to the
	  property value.</t>

	  <t>A floating-point value's TXT RDATA uses the representation
	  of an unsuffixed "floating constant" as defined in the C
	  programming language standard <xref target="ISO.9899.1990"
	  />. The representation MUST be specified using a single
	  &lt;character-string&gt; <xref target="RFC1034" />.</t>

	  <t>For example, if a catalog zone is named
	  "catalog1.example.org." and contains a property "decay-rate"
	  with value 0.15, the corresponding RR may appear as
	  follows:</t>

	  <figure>
	    <artwork>
        decay-rate.catalog1.example.org. 3600 IN TXT "15e-2"
	    </artwork>
	  </figure>

	  <t>Here, "decay-rate" can contain multiple TXT RRs at that
	  node of the domain name space <xref target="RFC1034" />. The
	  single floating-point property SHOULD be checked by the
	  implementation.</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Single domain names" anchor="sec-sname">
	  <t>A property with a single domain name as value is specified
	  using a PTR RR <xref target="RFC1035" /> with owner name set
	  to the name of the property as a sub-domain of the catalog
	  zone name, and RDATA set to the property value.</t>

	  <t>For example, if a catalog zone is named
	  "catalog1.example.org." and contains a property "prop1" with
	  value "val1.example.com.", the corresponding RR would appear
	  as follows:</t>

	  <figure>
	    <artwork>
        prop1.catalog1.example.org. 3600 IN PTR val1.example.com.
	    </artwork>
	  </figure>

	  <t>Here, "prop1" can contain multiple PTR RRs at that node of
	  the domain name space <xref target="RFC1034" />. The single
	  domain name property SHOULD be checked by the
	  implementation.</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Unordered list of domain names" anchor="sec-unolist">
	  <t>Let N be an absolute name formed by concatenating the RDATA
	  hash (see <xref target="sec-glossary" />), the name of the
	  property, and the catalog zone name in that order, such that N
	  is a unique owner name in the catalog zone.</t>

	  <t>Then, a property containing an unordered list of names as
	  value is specified using multiple PTR RRs <xref
	  target="RFC1035" /> with owner name set to N, and each RR's
	  RDATA set to each domain name in the list of the property's
	  value respectively.</t>

	  <t>For example, if a catalog zone is named
	  "catalog1.example.org." and contains a property "prop2" with
	  its value being an unordered list of two names
	  "a.example.com." and "b.example.com.", the corresponding RRs
	  would appear as follows:</t>

	  <figure>
	    <artwork>
        &lt;hash1&gt;.prop2.catalog1.example.org. 3600 IN PTR a.example.com.
        &lt;hash2&gt;.prop2.catalog1.example.org. 3600 IN PTR b.example.com.
	    </artwork>
	  </figure>

	  <t>Here, "prop2"'s subtree child nodes (in the domain name
	  space <xref target="RFC1034" />) can contain multiple PTR RRs
	  at each child. For example, &lt;hash1&gt;.prop2 may contain
	  multiple PTR RRs at that node. The single domain name property
	  SHOULD be checked by the implementation.</t>
	</section>

	<section title="List of network addresses" anchor="sec-network">
	  <t>A property with a list of network addresses as value is
	  specified using a single APL RR <xref target="RFC3123" /> with
	  owner name set to the name of the property as a sub-domain of
	  the catalog zone name, and RDATA set to the property value. In
	  its presentation format, the "!" character (corresponding to
	  the negation flag) is used to negate a network element. The
	  exact meaning of a negated network element is left to be
	  described by the property that APL is used for. Note that the
	  AFL RR TYPE is defined only for the IN(1) RR CLASS.</t>

	  <t>For example, if a catalog zone is named
	  "catalog1.example.org." and contains a property "allow-query"
	  with value [192.0.2.0/24, 198.51.100.0/24] as the list of
	  networks, the corresponding RR would appear as follows:</t>

	  <figure>
	    <artwork>
        allow-query.catalog1.example.org. 3600 IN APL (
                1:192.0.2.0/24 2:2001:db8::/32)
	    </artwork>
	  </figure>

	  <t>Here, "allow-query" can contain multiple APL RRs at that
	  node of the domain name space <xref target="RFC1034" />. The
	  single APL RR property SHOULD be checked by the
	  implementation.</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Single host address">
	  <t>A single host address is represented using the list of
	  network addresses data type (see <xref target="sec-network"
	  />) with a suitable network and prefix to result in a single
	  host address.</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Comments">
	  <t>Comments may be added anywhere in a catalog zone using a
	  scheme such as NOTE RRs <xref target="I-D.hunt-note-rr"
	  />. This memo does not depend on NOTE RRs and it is only
	  suggested here as an informative reference.</t>
	</section>

      </section>

      <section title="Catalog zone schema version">
	<t>The catalog zone schema version is specified by an unsigned
	integer property with the property name "version". All catalog
	zones MUST have this property present. Primary and secondary
	nameservers MUST NOT use catalog zones with an unexpected value
	value in this property, but they may be transferred as ordinary
	zones. For this memo, the "version" property value MUST be set
	to 1.</t>

	<t>For example, if a catalog zone is named
	"catalog1.example.org.", the corresponding RR MUST look as
	follows:</t>

	<figure>
	  <artwork>
        version.catalog1.example.org. 3600 IN TXT "1"
	  </artwork>
	</figure>

	<t>Here, "version" can contain multiple TXT RRs at that node of
	the domain name space <xref target="RFC1034" />. The single TXT
	RR property SHOULD be checked by the implementation.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="List of member zones">
	<t>The list of member zones are specified as an unordered list
	(see <xref target="sec-unolist" />) of names under the owner
	name "zones" where "zones" is a sub-domain of the catalog
	zone.</t>

	<t>The names of member zones are represented on the RDATA side
	instead of as part of owner names so that all valid domain names
	may be represented regardless of their length. <xref
	target="RFC1035" /></t>

	<t>For example, if a catalog zone is named
	"catalog1.example.org." and lists 3 zones "example.com.",
	"example.net." and "example.org.", the RRs would appear as
	follows:</t>

	<figure>
	  <artwork>
        &lt;hash&gt;.zones.catalog1.example.org. 3600 IN PTR example.com.
        &lt;hash&gt;.zones.catalog1.example.org. 3600 IN PTR example.net.
        &lt;hash&gt;.zones.catalog1.example.org. 3600 IN PTR example.org.
	  </artwork>
	</figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Zone configuration properties" anchor="sec-properties">
	<t>TBD: Prepare a list of zone configuration properties that are
	common to DNS implementations. This is so that a company may
	manage a catalog zone using a Windows DNS server as the primary,
	and a secondary nameserver hosting service may pick up the
	common properties and may use a different nameserver
	implementation such as BIND or NSD on a POSIX operating system
	to serve it.</t>

	<t>TBD: We may specify that unrecognized zone property names
	must be ignored, or that nameserver specific properties must be
	specified using the "x-" prefix similar to MIME type naming.</t>

	<t>TBD: Any list of zone properties is ideally maintained as a
	registry rather than within this memo.</t>

	<section title="zone-soa-default-serial">
	  <t>TBD.</t>
	</section>
	<section title="zone-soa-default-refresh">
	  <t>TBD.</t>
	</section>
      </section>

      <section title="Zone properties specific to a member zone">
	<t>Member zones in a catalog zone share template zone
	configuration that is common to all member zones in that
	catalog. This section describes the syntax that can be used to
	specify zone properties specific to single member zones.</t>

	<t>Let N be an absolute name formed by concatenating the member
	zone name hash as a label (see <xref target="sec-glossary" />),
	the label "zones", and the catalog zone name in that order, such
	that N is a unique owner name in the catalog zone.</t>

	<t>Zone properties specific to a particular member zone are
	specified under the respective sub-domain N.</t>

	<t>For example, if a catalog zone is named
	"catalog1.example.org." and a member zone "example.com."
	contains a property "prop0" with string (see <xref
	target="sec-string" />) value "Example", the corresponding RR
	would appear as follows:</t>

	<figure>
	  <artwork>
        prop0.&lt;m-hash&gt;.zones.catalog1.example.org. 3600 IN TXT "Example"
	  </artwork>
	</figure>

	<t>As another example, if a catalog zone is named
	"cat1.example.org." and a member zone "example.com."  contains a
	property "prop2" with its value being an unordered list (see
	<xref target="sec-unolist" />) of two names "a.example.com."
	and "b.example.com.", the corresponding RRs would appear as
	follows:</t>

	<figure>
	  <artwork>
        (&lt;hash&gt;.prop2.&lt;m-hash&gt;.zones.cat1.example.org.
         3600 IN PTR a.example.com.)
        (&lt;hash&gt;.prop2.&lt;m-hash&gt;.zones.cat1.example.org.
         3600 IN PTR b.example.com.)
	  </artwork>
	</figure>

      </section>

      <section title="Example of a catalog zone">
	<figure>
	  <artwork>
            $ORIGIN catalog.example.org.
            @           IN SOA  . . 1 3600 3600 86400 3600
                        IN NS   invalid.
            version     IN TXT  "1"
            (5960775ba382e7a4e09263fc06e7c00569b6a05c.zones
             IN PTR domain1.example.com.)
	  </artwork>
	</figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Nameserver behavior and requirements" anchor="sec-impl">
      <section title="General requirements">
	<t>TBD: Explain nameserver behavior in a more detailed way
	here. It is under-specified.</t>

	<t>As it is a regular DNS zone, a catalog zone can be
	transferred using DNS zone transfers among nameservers.</t>

	<t>Although they are regular DNS zones, catalog zones contain
	only information for the management of a set of nameservers.
	For this reason, operators may want to limit the systems able to
	query these zones. It may be inconvenient to serve some contents
	of catalog zones via DNS queries anyway due to the nature of
	their representation. A separate method of querying entries
	inside the catalog zone may be made available by nameserver
	implementations (see <xref target="sec-notes" />).</t>

	<t>Catalog updates should be automatic, i.e., when a nameserver
	that supports catalog zones completes a zone transfer for a
	catalog zone, it SHOULD apply changes to the catalog within the
	running nameserver automatically without any manual
	intervention.</t>

	<t>As with regular zones, primary and secondary nameservers for
	a catalog zone may be operated by different administrators. The
	secondary nameservers may be configured to synchronize catalog
	zones from the primary, but the primary's administrators may not
	have any administrative access to the secondaries.</t>

	<t>A catalog zone can be updated via DNS UPDATE on a reference
	primary nameserver, or via zone transfers. Nameservers MAY allow
	loading and transfer of broken zones with incorrect catalog zone
	syntax (as they are treated as regular zones), but nameservers
	MUST NOT process such broken zones as catalog zones. For the
	purpose of catalog processing, the broken catalogs MUST be
	ignored. If a broken catalog zone was transferred, the newly
	transferred catalog zone MUST be ignored (but the older copy of
	the catalog zone SHOULD be left running subject to values in SOA
	fields).</t>

	<t>If there is a clash between an existing member zone's name
	and an incoming member zone's name (via transfer or update), the
	new instance of the zone MUST be ignored and an error SHOULD be
	logged.</t>

	<t>When zones are introduced into a catalog zone, a primary
	SHOULD first make the new zones available for transfers before
	making the updated catalog zone available for transfer, or
	sending NOTIFY for the catalog zone to secondaries. Note that
	secondary nameservers may attempt to transfer the catalog zone
	upon refresh timeout, so care must be taken to make the member
	zones available before any update to the list of member zones is
	visible in the catalog zone.</t>

	<t>When zones are deleted from a catalog zone, a primary MAY
	delete the member zone immediately after notifying
	secondaries. It is up to the secondary nameserver to handle this
	condition correctly.</t>

	<t>TBD: Transitive primary-secondary relationships</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Updating catalog zones">
	<t>TBD: Explain updating catalog zones using DNS UPDATE.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Implementation notes" anchor="sec-notes">
	<t>Catalog zones on secondary nameservers would have to be setup
	manually, perhaps as static configuration, similar to how
	ordinary DNS zones are configured. Members of such catalog zones
	will be automatically synchronized by the secondary after the
	catalog zone is configured.</t>

	<t>An administrator would want to look at data inside a catalog
	zone. Typical queries may include dumping the list of member
	zones, dumping a member zone's effective configuration, querying
	a specific property value of a member zone, etc.  Because of the
	syntax of catalog zones, it may not be possible to perform these
	queries intuitively, or in some cases, at all, using DNS
	QUERY. The list of member zones may not fit in a single DNS
	message. The set of present properties for a zone cannot be
	queried using a single DNS QUERY.</t>

	<t>Implementations are advised to provide a tool that uses
	either the output of AXFR or an out-of-band method to perform
	queries on catalog zones.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security considerations">
      <t>As catalog zones are transmitted using DNS zone transfers, it
      is absolutely essential for these transfers to be protected from
      unexpected modifications on the route. So, it is a requirement
      that catalog zone transfers SHOULD be authenticated using TSIG <xref
      target="RFC2845" />. A primary nameserver SHOULD NOT serve a catalog
      zone for transfer without using TSIG and a secondary nameserver
      SHOULD abandon an update to a catalog zone that was received without
      using TSIG.</t>

      <t>DNS UPDATE <xref target="RFC2136" /> to catalog zones similarly
      SHOULD be authenticated using TSIG.</t>

      <t>Zone transfers of member zones SHOULD similarly be
      authenticated using TSIG <xref target="RFC2845" />. The TSIG
      shared secrets used for member zones MUST NOT be mentioned
      anywhere in the catalog zone data. However, key identifiers may be
      shared within catalog zones.</t>

      <t>Catalog zones do not need to be signed using DNSSEC; their zone
      transfers being authenticated by TSIG. Signed zones MUST be
      handled normally by nameservers, and their contents MUST NOT be
      DNSSEC-validated.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA considerations">
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Catalog zones originated as the chosen method among various
      proposals that were evaluated at ISC for easy zone management. The
      chosen method of storing the catalog as a regular DNS zone was
      proposed by Stephen Morris.</t>

      <t>We later discovered that Paul Vixie's earlier <xref
      target="Metazones" /> proposal implemented a similar approach and
      reviewed it. Catalog zones borrows some syntax ideas from
      Metazones, as both share this scheme of representing the catalog
      as a regular DNS zone.</t>

      <t>Thanks to Brian Conry, Evan Hunt, and Victoria Risk for
      reviewing draft proposals and providing support, comments and
      suggestions.</t>

      <t>Thanks to BIND users who reviewed draft proposals and offered
      comments and suggestions.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative references">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1034.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1035.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1982.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2136.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2606.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2845.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3123.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7719.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.ISO.9899.1990.xml"?>

      <reference anchor="FIPS.180-4.2015" target="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/fips/fips180-4/fips-180-4.pdf">
	<front>
	  <title>Secure Hash Standard</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>National Institute of Standards and Technology</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date month="August" year="2015" />
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="FIPS" value="PUB 180-4" />
      </reference>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative references">
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.hunt-note-rr.xml"?>
      <reference anchor="RPZ" target="http://ftp.isc.org/isc/dnsrpz/isc-tn-2010-1.txt">
	<front>
	  <title>DNS Response Policy Zones (DNS RPZ)</title>
	  <author fullname="Paul Vixie" initials="P." surname="Vixie" />
	  <author fullname="Vernon Schryver" initials="V." surname="Schryver" />
	  <date year="2010" />
	</front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="Metazones" target="http://ss.vix.su/~vixie/mz.pdf">
	<front>
	  <title>Federated Domain Name Service Using DNS Metazones</title>
	  <author fullname="Paul Vixie" initials="P." surname="Vixie" />
	  <date year="2005" />
	</front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section title="Glossary" anchor="sec-glossary">
      <t>
	<list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">

	  <t hangText="Catalog zone:">A DNS zone containing a DNS
	  catalog, that is, a list of DNS zones and associated template
	  zone configuration common to all member zones.</t>

	  <t hangText="Member zone:">A DNS zone whose configuration is
	  published inside a catalog zone.</t>

	  <t hangText="Primary nameserver:">An authoritative server
	  configured to be the source of zone transfer to one or more
	  [secondary] nameservers. Also see <xref target="RFC7719"
	  />.</t>

	  <t hangText="RDATA hash:">The hexadecimal format 40-digit
	  SHA-1 <xref target="FIPS.180-4.2015" /> digest, of the RDATA
	  of the corresponding RR. For RDATA containing DNS names, no
	  name compression must be in use, i.e., the name must be in its
	  full expanded wire data format when it is hashed.</t>

	  <t hangText="Member zone name hash:">The hexadecimal format
	  40-digit SHA-1 <xref target="FIPS.180-4.2015" /> digest, of a
	  zone name in uncompressed wire format.</t>

	  <t hangText="Secondary nameserver:">An authoritative server
	  which uses zone transfer to retrieve the zone. Also see <xref
	  target="RFC7719" />.</t>

	  <t hangText="Zone property:">A configuration parameter of a
	  zone, sometimes also called a zone option.</t>

	</list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Open issues and discussion (to be removed before final publication)">
      <t><list style="numbers">
	<t>Config options
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	We want catalog zones to be adopted by multiple DNS
	implementations. Towards this, we have to generalize zone
	config options and adopt a minimal set that we can expect
	most implementations to support.
	</t>
	<t>Catalog zone and member zones on different primary
	nameservers
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	Will it be possible to setup a catalog zone on one nameserver as
	primary, and allow its member zones to be served by different
	primary namesservers?
	</t>
	<t>Transitive relationships
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	For a catalog zone, a secondary nameserver may be a primary
	nameserver to a different set of nameservers in a nameserver
	farm. In these transitive relationships, zone configuration
	options (such as also-notify and allow-transfer) may differ
	based on the location of the primary in the hierarchy. It may
	not be possible to specify this within a catalog zone.
	</t>
	<t>Templates
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	Are support for config and zone data templates useful at this
	level? They would add complexity across implementations. If
	added, it would be better to restrict templates at the primary
	nameserver and let the secondary receive regular expanded zones.
	</t>
	<t>Overriding controls
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	A way to override zone config options (as prescribed by the
	catalog zones) on secondary nameservers was requested. As this
	would be configured outside catalog zones, it may be better to
	leave this to implementations.
	</t>
	<t>Use of hashing
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	Should use of hashing be completely removed, and replaced with
	the same common owner name for all property RRs in a collection?
	Both IXFR and DNS UPDATE allow changing individual RRs in a
	RRset.
	</t>
	<t>Choice of hash function
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	Should a different faster hash function be chosen to replace
	SHA-1 when computing catalog member zone name hashes?
	</t>
	<t>Overriding existing RR types
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	This memo currently overrides only the PTR RR TYPE's meaning as
	PTR is currently used for reverse lookups. But such overridden
	use seems like a non-issue as PTR is defined to be a pointer to
	any name in <xref target="RFC1035" />.
	</t>
	<t>APL limits
	<vspace blankLines="1"/>
	APL can only support as many networks as can fit in its
	RDATA. Though a very large number of networks can be listed in a
	single RDATA field, it is still limited in size. Will this
	limitation become a problem for any users?
	</t>
      </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Change History (to be removed before final publication)">
      <t>
	<list style="symbols">

	  <t>
	    draft-muks-dnsop-dns-catalog-zones-00
	    <vspace/>
	    Initial public draft.
	  </t>

	  <t>
	    draft-muks-dnsop-dns-catalog-zones-01
	    <vspace/>
	    Added Witold, Ray as authors. Fixed typos, consistency
	    issues. Fixed references. Updated Area. Removed newly
	    introduced custom RR TYPEs. Changed schema version to
	    1. Changed TSIG requirement from MUST to SHOULD. Removed
	    restrictive language about use of DNS QUERY. When zones are
	    introduced into a catalog zone, a primary SHOULD first make
	    the new zones available for transfers first (instead of
	    MUST). Updated examples, esp. use IPv6 in examples per Fred
	    Baker. Add catalog zone example.
	  </t>

	</list>
      </t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
